Guide to the Ronald R. Spadafora Papers 1911-2018 (bulk, 1970s-2010s) MS 3134
New-York Historical Society
- World Trade Center, circa 2001-2007 (Offsite-box 9894)
  Incident action plans for Sept 2001-June 2002 (end of project). Powerpoint slides re: health & safety Issues at WTC (2002). Snapshots, looks like Spadafora visiting Kansas City, August 2002. Packet of material that relates at least in part to Spadafora's presentation at the Illinois Fire Chiefs Association (IFCA) in Waukegan, 2003, with Powerpoint slides re: WTC "FDNY: Facing Future Challenges with ICS" and WTC timeline, notes on McKinsey report, etc. Printout from web of McKinsey report "Increasing FDNY's Preparedness" (2002). Packet re: Spadafora's presentation at Mt. Sinai re: WTC health & safety (CD and slides) (2002). WTC damaged buildings grids. Certificate of appreciation from DoL for implementing the WTC emergency project environmental safety and health plan (2002). Binder of preparatory documents for the OSHA WTC Emergency Response Incident Critique held in June 2002 in Absecon, NJ. Snapshots (prints and on floppy and disks) of Ground Zero recovery (2002). Various print matter (some tearsheets, 9/11 commission report, Ground Zero book with inserts, FDNY "Helping America Cope" booklet). There is also one file related to the WTC Human Remains Recovery Project of 2006-07 with several incident action plans. (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center, circa 2001-2011 (Offsite-box 9884)
  Pile of materials related to WTC and recovery operations. Includes things sent to Spadafora in response to 9/11: Photograph with double exposure of standing WTC and Ground Zero (backstory by photographer with photo); some sympathy cards; some drawings/artwork; photo of firefighter Gary Geidec who died on 9/11; children's drawings. Book "Closure" by Lt. William Keegan Jr inscribed by author to Spadafora. Book "The Guys." Photo of Spadafora at "Last Day of Ground Zero, May 30, 2002, Closing Ceremony" taken by Gary Susan. Various memos (document preservation, etc.), lists of missing FDNY members/identified/kin notifications, lab results from debris samples for PCBs etc, debris handling procedures. Many articles, tearsheets about 9/11 and remains recovery. Much material from 2001-02, but also much press material from ten year anniversary in 2011. WTC Medical Monitoring report for Spadafora, 2001-02. Response of FDNY to the NY Post's "tasteless" cartoon of Dec 2, 2003, apparently re: firefighters striking up relationships with dead firefighters' wives. Includes FDNY Dept Order 61 of July 4, 2003, which "caught up" on a complete list with photos of all members who died on 9/11/01. Booklets re: commissioning of USS New York (Nov 7, 2009). Packet of vendor material on a facepiece respirator with artifact respirator included. Metal plate "No whining." (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center / 130 Liberty (1 of 2), 1970s-2007 (Offsite-box 9888)
  Entire box appears to relate to FDNY's investigation into the fatal injury to firefighters Joseph Graffagnino and Robert Beddia at 130 Liberty Street (Deutsche Bank buildng) on Aug 18, 2007. The final Investigative Report is in the box (with FDNY's CD with WAV file with transmission from the firefighting battalion). Rest of box holds original "01 files" for 130 Liberty (which went by other addresses (a/k/a) as well in the files, most commonly One Bankers Trust Plaza) and nearby addresses. These other addresses include 30 West Broadway and 130 Cedar's 8th floor location of Stillwell & Gladding Inc. Though the forwarding and some other documents date from the 2007 investigation, the files themselves hold documents from the 1970s-1990s, and appear to relate primarily to fire inspections, findings, violations, and the like, with reports, site and other plans, etc. According to a memo in the box, generally "the Bureau of Fire Prevention generates the documents contained in the 01 File, although the 01 File is maintained by the Public Records Unit, which is part of the Bureau of Legal Affairs." (130 Liberty was damaged in the 9/11 attack and was vacant at the time of the 2007 incident; no other WTC connnection here.) (Content continues in box 9889.) (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center / 130 Liberty (2 of 2), 1970s-2007 (Offsite-box 9889)
  Continuation from box 9888 re: investigation of 130 Liberty (Deutsche Bank building/One Bankers Trust Plaza) incident in 2007. This box holds two 01 files and related materials for 30 West Broadway and 130 Liberty. The related material for 130 Liberty includes copies of documents from the Lower Manhattan Development Corp (LMDC): Emergency Action Plan for the 130 Liberty Deconstruction Project (2005), 130 Liberty Deconstruction Implementation Plan (2006), and 130 Liberty Asbestos & Contaminants of Potential Concern Abatement & Removal Plan (2005). CD of 130 Liberty fire suppression unit photos (2004). (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center, circa 2002-2007 (Offsite-box 9881)
  WTC Potential Human Remains (PHR) Recovery related: Site Specific Health & Safety Plans (drafts & final) for WTC Haul Road, Off-Site sifting in at 11 Water St in Brooklyn, pre-sifting operation at WTC 39th Street Pier, and exploratory excavations; draft plan to implement report recommendations for additional PHR searches at WTC. Tearsheets, web pages, memos, etc. (all 2006-07). CD of FDNY photos of WTC PHR Project. Final FDNY Recovery Team report (set of memos), June 10, 2002. Also files on investigation into 130 Liberty Street (Deutsche Bank/One Bankers Trust Plaza) firefighter fatal injury (Graffignino/Beddia: Vol 1 of Report plus incident action plan, pre-fire plan, etc. (2007). Logbook of manpower (WTC-related, but not clear as to exactly how), 2006-07.(Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center, circa 2007 (Offsite-box 9882)
  About half of box relates to WTC Potential Human Remains (PHR) project (2007): status reports, manpower, emails, and the like. Other half of box relates to 130 Liberty Street matter: clippings, tearsheets, building deconstruction plan, etc. But there is overlap with documents regarding PHR project at 130 Liberty.
- World Trade Center, circa 2007-2014 (Offsite-box 9887)
  A large pile of loose papers re: WTC, 2007-14. Some things that stood out: health & safety plan for forensic sifting operations at JFK Airport (2011); WTC Phase IV Sifting Operations at Fresh Kills Landfill 2013; Reports/reconciliations on PHR (Potential Human Remains) locations and totals found, especially daily reports from Fresh Kills operation; OCME daily Situation Reports; 51 Park Place and 130 Cedar Street related reports and emails; photocopies of agreements to donate FDNY vehicles to museums; reports of specifically identified remains by individual; WTC Office of Chief Medical Examiner Operational statistics; Remediation and Deconstruction of Fiterman Hall 2006. Photographs of a small award/recognition event; there are CDs labeled WTC recovery award group shots, so likely is that (2009). Print-outs of emails to Spadafora on the subject matter. Print-outs of web articles from news outlets on the human remains subject. (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center, circa 2004-2011 (Offsite-box 9897)
  All WTC related. Thick folder of tearsheets, webpage prints re: "progressive collapse" (i.e., building collapses vertically rather than topples), with a CD of a YouTube editorial on building collapse; these articles relate to both WTC specifically and design matter generally (circa 2004-11). Booklets on the health impact of WTC (circa 2007), including specifically on FDNY rescue workers; also a thick folder of tearsheets etc on health impact (Spadafora's filing with FDNY as working at Ground Zero is in here among webpage prints). Report "Investigation of Administrative Issues Relating to the Fatal Fire of August 18, 2007 at 130 Liberty Street", with attachments (2009). Draft (public) of NIST report on the collapse of WTC building 7 (collapsed at 5:20 on 9/11), 2008. Print matter: Langewiesche's book "American Ground." Several CDs and DVDs re: WTC 7 collapse (2007-08), 1 WTC walkthrough and standpipe test (2012), WTC Building Code Task Force, Freedom Tower, WTC Gallery Photos 11/11. (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center (2 oversize folders), circa 2007 (Folder FF1, 2)
  2 oversize folders of WTC Potential Human Remains (PHR) project maps/grids (e.g., aerial photos of Ground Zero overlaid with grids marked to show where remains were found), and an unrelated poster re: Field Communications Systems.
- World Trade Center. Reference., circa 1999-2002 (Offsite-box 9555)
  9/11 Commission report with inserts re: release of additional FDNY recordings. A set of 23 CDs re: 9/11/01 with EMS dispatch recordings, Brooklyn & Manhattan Fire dispatch recordings, Port Authority radio repeater audio, and FDNY oral histories. Print matter on fire evacuations in general. A print of a PDF of "Comprehensive Review of the Chicago Fire Department" 1999. Folder of print matter on radio communications. Laminated charts of WTC 1 and 2. Binder: Instruction Kit, WTC Emergency Project, New Employee Orientation Training (building trades effort to improve worker safety), Nov. 5, 2001. Binder of material from FEMA re: Fire in the US, 1992-2001. (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center. Specifics (Staten Island brush fire), circa 2002-2009 (Offsite-box 9734)
  Bulk of box holds files re: WTC (draft building performance study of 2002, photocopies of articles, lessons learned articles, medical/health aftermath, emails etc re a defamation suit of circa 2005 or so). There are also a couple files concerning a 2009 Staten Island brush file, with floppies, CDs as well as paper. (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center. Education. Reference., circa 1998-2011 (Offsite-box 9852)
  Print matter re: WTC including "FDNY 2001-2011…" (still shrink-wrapped), 2 slightly different "World Trade Center: The Giants that Defied the Sky" by Peter Skinner, and "New York: September 11" by Magnum Photographers. A rolled oversize photo of firefighters raising flag at Ground Zero. A roll of floor plans for 130 Liberty Street, dated 2002. Rest of material refers to incident management generally: Binders for Domestic Preparedness Training (defense against weapons of mass destruction): Incident Command Course and Responder Awareness Course. Homeland Security's National Incident Management System (NIMS), final draft of 2003 and "Emergency Response to Terrorism: Operations", Student Manual (2004). FEMA "Incident Command System" independent study course, 1998. Laminated CIMS reference guide. FDNY Incident Management Team (IMT) booklets "Internet Resource Guide" (2008) and "2007 Year in Review." Department order recruiting for IMT (2008). Documents and DVD (3 copies) re: BIOPOD and the IMT re: drill for responding to a flu breakout (2007 refers to avian flu, and 2010 to flu generally). (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center. Reference. Personal., circa 1993-2008 (Offsite-box 9883)
  Binder of materials from the National Association of Hispanic Firefighters training conference, Dallas, 2007: Spadafora presented on "9/11 Lessons Learned" docs include conference program and hand-outs, which include a speaker from Shreveport's slides on Hurricane Katrina Lessons Learned; Spadafora's binder holds various reference materials (FDNY annual report FY2006, FDNY terrorism & disaster preparedness strategy 2007, FDNY strategic plan 2007-08, some AUMs, CIMS/incident management protocol, various notes/outlines and CDs of photos and Powerpoint). Thick binder labeled "WTC circulars": starts 9/21/01 with 0700 Incident Command Post Meeting summary and proceeds through 387 informally numbered pages to June 2002 (handwritten table of contents at front (Spadafora was designated FDNY Safety Officer for the entire Recovery Operation at WTC, which dated according to Spadafora Oct 2001-June 2002); pages include "WTC Command" reports (which include recovery reports among other matters), "WTC emergency project" bulletins from NYC Dept of Design & Construction (on health & safety protocols), staffing/admin memos, security, etc. Also has maps of "inner zone as of 11/5/01" "safety area where gear is needed at all times", "WTC Recovery Project: Memorial Service Logistics" (Oct 24, 2001). Loose papers in box include a certification by Spadafora re: retired FDNY member Jacob E. Schiavone recovery work at site (2007); news articles/tearsheets/FDNY orders, etc. about the recovery; also Rhonda Shearer's extended response to the "American Ground" stolen goods contention (2003-06). Art Science Research Laboratory (Shearer and Gould) proposed project "WTC Living History Project by the People Who Actually Ran Ground Zero." (2002). Set of about 20 color 8x11 official FDNY photos of Ground Zero re: "crane collapse" of Nov 24, 2001. Portrait photo of Spadafora. Photo of Spadafora with Roger Clemens. Cheap print-outs of various Ground Zero digital photos. Certificate of recognition from NYC of Spadafora's work on WTC-PHR Recovery Project 2006-07. A few snapshots of Spadafora with others in diner, with motorcyclist, with Brooke Shields. Photo from Times (2002) of saluting a dumpster truck, presumably with remains. Clipboards with various WTC safety and other related memos. 2 floppies re: operations (one labeled "demobilization plan"). 2 CDs of "Danny Boy" by Susan "Scarlett" Ryan. 4 VHS: Wolf Blitzer of May 30, 2002; Kristin Heather re: PSA/Asbestos; FDNY on the scene: May 1993 WTC disaster; unopened weapons of mass destruction/first reponder tape from Dept of Justice. Artifact: Jesus on crucifix (metal; "Victor 02" on back, presumably creator and date). (Includes digital formats, artifacts, video)
- World Trade Center. Reference., circa 2002-2011 (Offsite-box 9851)
  Much of box holds print matter re: WTC/9/11, including: Special editions of magazines Firecall, Firefighters Quarterly, WNYF, LIFE, Fire Engineering, Firehouse. Reports and books: WTC Crisis Support Project Final Report; FDNY Memorial Day Oct 12, 2002 booklets; FDNY book "Helping America Cope"; print from web of US Fire Admin's "WTC Bombing (1993): Report & Analysis"; Powerpoint? of "Flight Recorder Recovery" with images and summary; Powerpoint by OSHA on WTC site safety (2002); Poynter Institute collection of newspaper front pages; "In the Line of Duty" book; "Ground Zero: Behind the Scenes, 10-year anniversary edition" book; "Trauma & Transformation at Ground Zero" book. Also various web print-outs etc of short WTC-related articles. A folder re: dispute over William Langewiesche's book "American Ground" in which he charges FDNY with looting at Ground Zero. A copy of book "100 Years on Duane Street (Ladder 1, Engine 7, Battalion 1)" history refers to WTC. Rest of box includes print matter on general firefighting, though these are probably there from a WTC context: wire rope user manual, safety equipment catalogs, crane & rigging training manual and related, respirator inspection, working safely with silica, various Powerpoint presentations on safety including fall protection. "A Firefighter's Night Before Christmas" small book.
- World Trade Center. Policies & Procedures. Reference. Personal., circa 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 9553)
  Most, though not all, of the materials appear to relate to Spadafora's writings on safety issues at WTC (for WNYF in 2002 and for American Journal of Industrial Medicine) and on the AFID (Apparatus Field Investigation Duty) form, which involves hotels, cabarets, etc checks. Print matter: "Brotherhood" re WTC and "Walter the Farting Dog" (children's book), Fire Safety Directors Course for Office Buildings, Hotels & Motels; history of the NY Board of Fire Underwriters; fire law handbook, fire prevention code of NYC. Powerpoint of High-Rise Unit on-site exam procedures, 2005. Powerpoint of ICC Code Development Process. Set of files with material on homeless shelters, social clubs, etc, seemingly in connection with WNYF article (4th/2005). Files on FDNY organization and proposed Bureau of Fire Prevention (BFP) reorganization, circa 2003. Spadafora and other business cards. Artifacts: Pins, "Heroes of 2001" guest ID/lanyard. WTC Respirator Card. Floppy discs of articles. Several CDs/DVDs: emergency planning procedures for employers, building code, AFID forms & curriculum, "FDNY Health and Safety Issues, WTC" Powerpoint, October 25, 2003 ceremony, others. (Includes digital formats, artifacts)
- World Trade Center. Education. Reference., circa 2004-2017 (Offsite-box 9544)
  Print matter: Homeland Security manuals on preparedness, National Incident Management System, Presidential directives 2004-2005 with binder re: Course Developers Handbook. Packet of information re: Spadafora going to Barcelona to speak at a European conference on fire services, 2013. Some files re NY strategic plan, 2015-17. Pile of miscellaneous tearsheets, course matter, procedures. CDs and DVDs on terrorism, WTC building code task force, 7 WTC tour with construction photos (May 2010), etc. (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center. Education. Reference., circa 2000s-2010s (Offsite-box 9422)
  Print matter: 2 books on high rises & firefighting. 2 books by Billy Goldfeder (Pass it on) with stories from firefighters; Spadafora contributed to both; box has light folders of related drafts. Book re: Deutsche Bank fire with inserts. Several CDs and DVDs from FDNY for training (elevator emergencies, facility operations, forcible entries, etc.). Many CDs (and DVDs?) of WTC-related photos, Powerpoint slides, and other material not specifically clear as to content; one notes it is of the collapse itself, others refer to safety at Ground Zero, etc. (Includes digital formats)
- World Trade Center. Reference., circa 1996-2008 (Offsite-box 9885)
  Training binder from vendor on Kidde's Fire Suppression System, using gas (1996) and Kidde manual on their CO2 suppression system (2001). Vendor manual from Sapphire on suppression system (2005). FDNY MARC (Management Appraisal, Reviews and Compliance) report for Division 11, Aug 2, 2001. News articles and other related print matter on WTC, especially collapse (WNYF articles, FEMA "WTC: Building Performance Study" of May 2002), including conspiracy theories, out to circa 2008. DVD of TLC show on collapse. DVD of History Channel show skyscraper firefighting. CDs of WTC 7 collapse simulation ("Progressive Collapse") 2008. WTC Command summaries of FDNY's reports on environmental health and safety at WTC (June 2002). (Includes digital formats)
- Education, circa 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 7432)
  NYFIRS User Manual (2002), with inserted later orders, etc related to the system (2001-07). Binders 39, 40, 45, 48 for company officer, battalion chief, and lieutenant's prep course fire tech training (floppies/CDs, procedures), 2009-2015. See scope note for list of all related binders 1-48 and the boxes they are in. (Includes digital formats)
- Education, circa 2000s (Offsite-box 9545)
  Spadafora files for courses taught at MCNY in the 2000s including Intro to Homeland Security and Emergency Communications, with student work, grade list, reading material. Several CDs including Barcelona-related Powerpoints, MCNY and terrorism related material. (Includes digital formats)
- Education, circa 2004-2006 (Offsite-box 9758)
  Print matter re: training. Binder for First Line Supervisors (FLSTP) (2004-06) course, Probationary Firefighters course, and Captains Course /Fire Prevention (with CD). Relates directly to box 9759 below. (Includes digital formats)
- Education, circa 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 9759)
  Print matter re training includes: 3 textbooks on general management. 4 catalogs/bulletins from John Jay College (2001-06). FLSTP (First Line Supervisors Training Program) material: 4 week curriculum overview (2004), "Code Enforcement & Referrals" course material for 2005-06. Probationary Firefighter School course material re code enforcement/summonses (NOVs/notice of violations procedures); there are several copies of the course material. Bound docs on "Fire Prevention", likely in connection with Battalion Chief Annual Training Day, for which there are a couple folders of material. A CD re: Captain's Day, 2005. There is a memo here providing an overview of the layers of training. (Relates directly to box 9758 above.) (Includes digital formats)
- Education, circa 1993 (Offsite-box 9793)
  Fire/arson seminar material, 1993. Police Academy training manual re criminal investigation course and related Fire Investigation course (both loose but formerly in binder, probaby the overstuffed one in the box that has other related material; see box 9794). Binder: "Police Students Guide-Law."
- Education, circa 1996-2013 (Offsite-box 9840)
  7 binders labeled with numbers: 3, 4, 7, 8, 11, 42, 46. All appear to relate to Spadafora teaching a fire tech course for officer promotions, years from about 1996 (book 3) to 2013 (book 46). See scope note for list of all related binders 1-48 and the boxes they are in.
- Education, circa 1980s-2002 (Offsite-box 9848)
  2 envelopes of course material for fire tech/firefighting training and trial exams, 1980s-90s. Print: "Fire Department Promotional Tests: A New Direction" by Matthew Murtagh of FDNY, 1993. Fire tech course "sampler" and other docs, 2000. 3 binders labeled "Lieutenant course" includes fire tech promotion class material/test questions, for 1999-2002 ("firefighting seminar series")
- Education, circa 1990s (Offsite-box 9753)
  Print matter re: training. Most of box relates to public education re: fire prevention, including textbooks on education, prevention materials aimed at children, school teacher handbooks, FDNY Community Newsletters. FEMA Student Manual re: Intermediate ICS (Incident Command System) for Expanding Incidents. Packets of study material for certification of fitness exams for air compressors, low PSI oil burners, and oil storage.
- Education, circa 1998-2008 (Offsite-box 9558)
  3 binders: 1) Incident Management Team Leadership, L-480, FDNY, materials provided by NAFRI (National Advanced Fire & Resource Institute), 2008 (Spadafora took multi-day course), some course related CDs. 2) Incident Command System National Training Curriculum, 1998, from NY State Emergency Management Office. 3) FDNY National Incident Management (Incident Command System), from National Advanced Resource Technology Center, 2003. Given by National Wildfire Coordinating group. (Includes digital formats)
- Education, circa 1970s-1990s (Offsite-box 9795)
  "Manual of Operations for Marine Companies", 1980s, revoked 1996. "Captains Course: Fire Operations Command", 1994. Pocket binder of some material for first line supervisors training, 1980s. Also a larger binder of "First Line Supervisors Training Program" (FLSTP), circa late 1970s, with later tearsheet inserts in pockets. Binder labeled "OITS" (Officers Induction Training School), 1970s training/orientation material (some references to "Lift program"). Binder labeled "Training Bulletins: APP-First Aid" but seems to have broader training material with core dating from 1970s-90s, with later tearsheets inserted by Spadafora. Binder labeled "Legislation," includes reference material on legal matters, both specific to firefighters and general (hiring). Binder labeled "CWD, 14-" includes various FDNY training/lesson plans, 1980s with later tearsheet etc inserts. Binder labeled "TBs: Tools" includes training material on saws, flashlights, masks, and other equipment, again 1980s-90s, with later inserts.
- Education, circa 1993-2010s (Offsite-box 9797)